Section 14 of Fables of Aesop and others.
This is a Librivox recording.
All Librivox recordings are in the public
domain. For more information or to
volunteer, please visit Librivox.org.
Recording by Lola of Northern Virginia.
Fables of Aesop and Others by Aesop.
The Two Pots. An earthen pot and one of
brass standing together upon the brink of
a river were both carried away by a sudden
rise of the water. The earthen pot showed
some uneasiness, fearing he should be
broken, but his companion of brass bade
him be under no apprehension,
as he would take care of him. Oh,
replies the other, keep as far off as you
can, I entreat you. It is you I am most
afraid of, for whether the stream dash you
against me or me against you,
I am sure to be the sufferer. Therefore,
I beg of you, do not let us come near one
another. Application. A man of moderate
fortune who is contented with what he has
and finds he can live happily upon it
should be particularly guarded against the
ill-judged ambition of associating with
the rich and powerful, for what in them is
economy would in him be the height of
extravagance. And at the very time they
honor him with their countenance,
they are leading him on to his ruin.
People of equal conditions may float down
the current of life without hurting each
other, but it's no easy matter to steer
one's course in company with the great so
as to escape without a bulge.
Neither is it desirable to live in the
neighborhood of a very great man,
for whether we ignorantly trespass upon
him or he knowingly encroach upon us,
we are sure to be the sufferers.
End of chapter 14.